Guide to the Laird Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Laird family papers
1890-1980
MS 1207
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(4 boxes, 1 folio)
The principal figures in these papers are Thelma Fae Laird, nurse and educator, and her immediate family. Photographs and memorabilia collected during her service in the Navy Nurse Corps during World War II make up the largest part of the papers. Also in the collection are the letters of her father, Allan Max Laird, on Wisconsin politics and of her mother, Sara O'Neil Laird, describing her life as a school teacher in Wisconsin at the turn of the century. The activities of her brother, Joseph M. Laird, and other members of the Laird and O'Neil families are reflected in family correspondence (1901-1954), photographs and memorabilia.
Laird family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Janet Grant Rudnicki, executrix of Thelma Laird's estate, 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
Correspondence and school records in Box 4 are closed until January 1, 2029.
Scope and Contents
The chief figure in the Laird Family Papers is Thelma Fae Laird, nurse and educator. The collection most fully documents her service in the Navy Nursing Corps during World War II, mostly in the South Pacific; there are letters to family, photographs, and printed matter and memorabilia from this period. But there are also materials from her school years, her work for the American Nurses' Association (1947-51), and her last academic position at Florence-Darlington Technical Education Center (1972-73). Her papers also contain a long and cordial correspondence with Bernard M. Baruch.
Thelma Laird's wartime letters to her parents make up most of the family correspondence. But the collection does include papers of Thelma's mother, Sara O'Neil Laird, concerning her work as a Wisconsin school teacher at the turn of the century; correspondence of her father, Allan Max Laird, concerning Wisconsin politics, a French lawsuit on behalf of his father's pearl business, and his work as a minister in Elmira, N.Y.; correspondence and obituary clippings concerning her brother, Joseph M. Laird; and other papers and photographs of various members of the Laird and O'Neil families.
There are also two folders of letters written by five servicemen to their families and friends. All were patients at the U.S. Navy Base Mobile Hospital #4 (c/o Fleet Post Office, San Francisco) in September 1943, when the letters were written; one serviceman mentions being in a malaria ward, while two others were receiving psychiatric treatment. Though the envelopes all have postage, none is postmarked. It is not known why the letters were not sent, or how they came into Thelma Laird's possession. These letters, and transcripts of Thelma Laird's school records, are closed to research for 75 years from the date of their creation.
The papers were given to Yale by Janet Grant Rudnicki, Executrix of Thelma Laird's Estate, in September 1980.
Biographical / Historical
Thelma Fae Laird: nurse; served in Navy Nursing Corps during World War II, and retired with rank of lieutenant commander; director of nursing at Memorial Hospital, Sloan Kettering Institute; on the faculty of University of Southern California at Berkeley; active in the American Cancer Society.
Families; World War, 1939-1945; Wisconsin -- Politics and government; Nurses; Women teachers; Laird, Allan Max; Laird, Sara O'Neil; Laird, Thelma Fae, 1908-1980; Laird family; O'Neill family
- Inventory
  - Family correspondence, 1901, 1906, 1927, 1929, 1942-1945, 1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 9)
  - Thelma Fae Laird
    - General correspondence, 1943-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with Bernard M. Baruch, 1951-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence and printed matter, including yearbook, re: Florence-Darlington Technical Education Center, S.C., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - School notes and papers: general, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - School papers re: nursing, [1934-1935], undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Writings, 1945-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Documents: birth certificate (photostat), divorce decree, diplomas, nurshing registrations, 1908-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Curriculum vitae and printed matter about Thelma Laird, including obituaries, 1946-1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Printed matter re: American Nurses' Association, 1951, 1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Printed matter and photographs re: Bernard M. Baruch and the Belle W. Baruch Foundation, 1954-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Printed matter from World War II, 1943-1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1960-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Photographs of Thelma Laird, 1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of South Pacific during World War II, with related letterPhotograph of Winston Churchill, one autographed, 1943-1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Memorabilia: addresses, calendars, calling cards, navy bar pin, 1963-65 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Sara O'Neil Laird: correspondence, letters of introduction, teacher's contracts and certificates, 1890-1901, 1918, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Sara O'Neil Laird [and Thelma Laird?]: notes and memorabilia, 1890-1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Allan Max Laird
    - Correspondence, 1902-1914, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 27 - 29)
    - Correspondence, 1920-1926, 1945, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Letters of recommendation, 1898-1904 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Writings, 1894, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Business and legal papers, printed memorabilia, silhouette, clippings, 1897-1924, 1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Joseph M. Laird: correspondence, obituary clippings, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Sara O'Neil Laird, Allan M. Laird, and other family members, 1938, 1949, 1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence and printed matter re: various family members of the O'Neil and Laird families, and unidentified correspondence, 1891-1969. undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Restricted material
    Conditions Governing Access
    Materials are restricted until January 1, 2029.
    - Thelma Laird: transcripts of grades, 1925-1954 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Letters from patients at U.S.N. Mobile Hospital #4 to their families and friends, 1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 38 - 39)
  - Oversize
    - Thelma Laird: diplomas, 1935, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Photographs: Thelma Laird, South Pacific, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Sara O'Neil Laird: teaching certificates, 1895, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 42)